<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ElliptiGO | Sapiary]]></title>
  <link href="http://josharian.github.com/blog/categories/elliptigo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josharian.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-10T19:01:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://josharian.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bleecher Snyder]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yet another ElliptiGO Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://josharian.github.com/blog/2012/03/11/elliptigo-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-11T11:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://josharian.github.com/blog/2012/03/11/elliptigo-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a year ago, I saw someone riding an <a href="http://www.elliptigo.com">ElliptiGO</a> near Dolores Park. I didn't know what it was, exactly, but I definitely wanted one. In case you've never seen one, here's one of their promo videos:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/67i6d9Hxjgg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Then I found out how much they cost (spoiler: a <em>lot</em>), and that dampened my ardor.</p>

<p>A full year later, I was still obsessing over them and boring my friends. I figured it was time to actually take one out for a test ride.</p>

<p>First stop was <a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/precor-home-fitness-san-mateo">Precor Home Fitness in San Mateo</a>. Alas, though they were very friendly, they only had a <a href="http://www.elliptigo.com/products/elliptigo-3c/">3C</a> to try (the bottom of the line), and they only let me ride it around in teeny tiny circus-bear circles in their fifteen foot parking lot.</p>

<p>Fortunately, <a href="http://www.blazingsaddles.com/san-francisco.aspx">Blazing Saddles in San Francisco</a> rents ElliptiGOs -- or rather, one sole ElliptiGO <a href="http://www.elliptigo.com/products/elliptigo-8c/">8C</a> at their Fisherman's Wharf location, which they told me they bought on a whim, and for which I was their first ever customer. So I summoned my courage and went willingly into the dark, tourist-infested heart of Fisherman's Wharf. I even took the cable car.</p>

<p>After some confusion at Blazing Saddles -- the ElliptiGO clearly didn't have a section in the employee handbook -- I escaped and took off west. I rode for an hour and a half, covering 17 miles, including a steep, sustained climb from the Golden Gate bridge up to the lookout at the Nike Missile site.</p>

<p><img src="img/elliptigo_and_sf.jpg" title="ElliptiGO overlooking SF" alt="ElliptiGO overlooking SF"></p>

<p>The experience was entirely novel, so I found in writing this review that I needed three lists: pros, cons, and flat out different.</p>

<h2>Pros</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Fun</strong>. It is just plain fun to ride. Really fun.</li>
<li><strong>Different</strong>. It is not biking. It is not running. It is definitely not swimming. And it's nice to have yet another way to get outside, get around, and get some exercise.</li>
<li><strong>Comfortable</strong>. It doesn't hurt your wrists, make your back or butt sore, inflame your prostate, or jar your ankles. It's possible that a lot of time with the ElliptiGO might be tough on the knees, but my first experience was just wonderful.</li>
<li><strong>Hill climbing</strong>. It's like rising out of the saddle to climb, but all the time, and comfortably. This thing was made for hills. I overtook a lot of cyclists in fancy gear during that long climb in Marin.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cons</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Bumpy ride</strong>. I don't know whether it is the tiny wheel radius or the lack of shocks, but you can feel every last pebble on the road, and on a particularly bad stretch of road near Crissy Field, it shook violently enough that I had to slow down to maintain control.</li>
<li><strong>Turning radius</strong>. The ElliptiGO was not made for darting in and out of traffic. It steers like a semi. Bike messengers and death wish commuters, this is not for you.</li>
<li><strong>Nowhere to rest</strong>. On a bike, you can rest your legs by putting the pedals level with each other. There is no single "resting" position on the ElliptiGO -- at least one foot is always tilted or extended, forwards or backwards.</li>
<li><strong>Heavy</strong>. 44 pounds.</li>
<li><strong>Loud</strong>. With every stride, the runners make a noisy, mechanical swish.</li>
<li><strong>Tunability</strong>. The stride length felt a little short to me, and I couldn't find any way to adjust it, with or without tools.</li>
<li><strong>Price</strong>. $2500 for the model I tried. That's pricy, even compared to a good quality road bike. And based on my parking lot experience, I wouldn't consider dropping down to the 3C, which is still $1800. I understand about economies of scale, and I know that ElliptiGO is a startup, and I sympathize...but the price is what the price is.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Different</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Shifting matters</strong>. Sometimes on a bike I just power up a hill without bothering to shift. Not so on the ElliptiGO. For any given speed and terrain, there is one and only one gear that is comfortable, so you shift much more frequently than on a bike. This is the most compelling reason to go for the higher end models -- they have more gears.</li>
<li><strong>Quad intensive</strong>. If you want to work your quads, this is the way. On a bike with clips, you can get a lot more of your leg into the action. Clips don't make sense on an ElliptiGO.</li>
<li><strong>Unknowns</strong>. By the end of the ride, I wasn't sure what shoes I would wear next time. (My running shoes felt clunky on it.) I wasn't sure how I would lock it in a bike rack. I wasn't sure how far 17 miles was in ElliptiGO terms. I wasn't sure how to give it a tune-up (and the rental needed one, particularly the derailleur), or where I could find an ElliptiGO mechanic in a pinch. I wasn't sure where I could buy replacement tires and tubes (the wheels are tiny!). Are there fenders for it? It's new and different.</li>
<li><strong>Fewer points of contact</strong>. On a bike, I can steer for blocks without my hands. On an ElliptiGO, there's no saddle, which is wonderful -- good for butts, backs, wrists, and prostates -- but it means that your hands are critical for stability. With some practice, I could drop down to a single hand for a short period of time, but even that felt dicey.</li>
<li><strong>Efficiency</strong>. In terms of effort-per-mile, I'd put the ElliptiGO between running and riding a mountain bike, although much closer to the mountain bike. It means you can get an intense workout more quickly, but also that it's not as good for covering long distances.</li>
<li><strong>Spectacle</strong>. I was unquestionably the center of attention for my whole ride, even in incredibly busy, crowded Crissy Field. People complimented me, bikers did double-takes, cars slowed down to stare, and several people asked to try it out. Every one of them came back with a grin on their face.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line</h2>

<p>All the ElliptiGO's faults are overlookable in the name of fun and exercise...except price. It's just a lot of money to spend on a vehicle that still feels rough around the edges. And that's a pity, because I still really want one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
